Isn’t it coalball, Dongbao?
冬宝 这不是煤球吗
No, it isn't.
这不是煤球
If I'm correct,
我要是没有认错的话
this is tungsten ore.
这个应该是钨砂
And these are bristles.
这个是猪鬃
These are all materials
这些都是
for weapons.
打仗用的东西啊
I've learned about it
我之前在
when I took the police training course.
警察培训班的时候学过
Munitions are military supplies
军需品是军队的配给
which can't be traded
不能当做
as normal goods.
普通的货物买卖
Is it smuggling?
会不会是走私啊
Who will these munitions be
走私打仗用的东西
smuggle to?
卖给谁啊
Do you know
你知不知道一号仓库
who rented the No.1 warehouse?
被什么人给租了
No.
不知道
Not even uncle Xu himself knows.
连徐伯伯自己都不知道
Well, you're not a police officer.
不是 冬宝
Dongbao.
你现在也不是警察了
You can do nothing about it.
拿这些能怎么办呢
Pack it up for me.
帮我包起来
What will you do?
你干吗呀
I'll bring them to the Anti-smuggling Department,
我要把这些
of General Maritime Customs Service Administration
送去江海关的
in Shanghai Customs District.
总税务司署缉私科
Anti-smuggling Department?
缉私科
It fights against smugglers.
就是专门查走私的地方
If the goods are
如果这些货物
suspicious,
真的有问题
they will follow up.
他们肯定会管的
It's dark outside,
这么大晚上了
you should take care.
你注意安全
Go back home as soon as possible.
早去早回
OK.
没事儿
Stay at home and wait for me.
你就在家等我回来
Easy.
慢 慢
Be careful on the way.
小心点儿啊
Nakamura Naoki.
里见先生
Have you finished tallying?
都点完货了吗
Not yet.
我们还在数
Why?
是因为什么
We lost one case.
少了一箱
It seemed that someone broke in from the window.
好像有人从窗户进来过
The warehouse is not safe anymore.
这个仓库不能用了
Bring several trucks.
叫货车来
Move all of them to HBS.
把这些都搬去弘济善堂
Move to our place?
搬到我们自己的地方吗
We can't find
这会儿也找不到
a safer place now.
更安全的地方
And the last batch of goods
反正最后一批货
will arrive here
也马上要从吴淞口
from Wusong Port.
运过来了
These goods
这些货
need to be stored at HBS
只用在弘济善堂
for only 2 or 3 days.
放个两三天
When the last batch of goods arrives,
等那批货
we'll ship them to Japan.
就全部装船运往日本
Hurry up.
手脚快点
Yes, Sir.
好的
Deputy.
副局长
I received it from section chief Gao from Anti-smuggling Dpt.
东西是江海关
of General Maritime Customs Service Administration
总税务司署
in Shanghai Customs District.
缉私科高科长给我的
Are they Nakamura Naoki's goods?
是里见仓库里的货
Yes.
是
Someone whistle-blew it
竟然有人
to the Anti-smuggling Dpt.,
扛着这箱东西
carrying the case.
去缉私科举报
This is the register information.
这是登记信息
This Tian Dongbao
这个叫田冬宝的
was a policeman from the Fourth Station.
之前是四所的
After the Fourth Station was closed,
四所撤了之后
he becomes a dock worker.
他就在码头扛货
In my opinion,
我觉得应该是
he happened to see the goods
他经过的时候
in the warehouse
碰巧发现了
when he passed by.
仓库里的东西
Have you checked the case?
箱子检查了吗
Yes.
检查了
Nothing is missing.
东西没少
And the customs police told him
而且关警的人
to keep it confidential
特意叮嘱过他要保密
He is an honest man
这个人很老实
and easy to deal with.
好解决
A bedbug.
臭虫一样的东西
Solve the problem.
解决了就行
Deputy,
副局长
more more thing,
还有件事儿
I've known the woman
之前在造船所医院
who stayed with
跟记者老婆在一起的
the wife
那个女人
of the reporter.
我查到了
She must know
她肯定知道
where the couple of the reporters are.
记者两口子在哪儿
However,
但是
she has a close relationship with Hua Zhen.
她跟华桢的关系很亲密
I wonder whether
我不知道
I can arrest her or not.
能不能动手
Don't you remember what I've told you?
我不是跟你说过吗
You can rely on me
你的后面
and
还有我
my back is covered by
我的后面
Nakamura Naoki.
还有里见先生
I'm back.
我回来了
Have you turned it in?
东西都交了
I did.
交了交了
They said they would investigate it.
他们说会核查的
If it has problems,
如果有问题
they'll solve them.
他们肯定会处理的
Warm yourself by the fire.
快烤火去
Dongbao,
冬宝
could it bring any trouble
我们该不会
on us?
有什么麻烦吧
No.
不会
The customs police said I did the right thing.
关警都说我做得对了
If the goods are smuggling articles,
如果那批货真的有问题
the police will
那有麻烦的
be troubled.
也是他们
They registered
关警还让我
my household information.
登记了户籍卡
They will
说要把我登记在那个
put my name on the list of
遵纪守法好市民的
good citizens.
名单上
They asked me to keep it confidential.
他让咱先保密
If there were any leak of information,
说走漏了风声
the criminal could have escaped.
他们就不好抓人了
Don't tell anyone else.
咱谁都别说啊
I got it.
知道了
Well,
对了
I've an appointment
我今天晚上
with the team.
跟车队约好了
We'll set off
集合
early in the morning.
凌晨出发
I must go shortly.
那我一会儿就走了
I haven't packed up my lugage yet.
我行李还没收拾呢
You stay and I'll pack up for you.
你歇着 我去
Dongbao,
冬宝
how long will you be back this time?
你这趟拉货几天回来
2 or 3 days.
两三天吧
Could you please not go?
就不能不去了吗
With one injured hand,
你看你一只手伤着
you can't do much.
也干不了什么活
Why not just have a rest at home?
还不如在家休息
I don't need to haul bags this time,
我这次去不用搬货
They need someone who guards the goods
晚上他们睡觉的时候
on the car in case of thieves
需要有一个人
when sleeping
看车上的货
at night.
免得遭小偷
I just need to guard the goods.
我就是去看货的
You should get sleep, too.
他们睡觉你也得睡觉啊
Not necessarily.
我就不用睡了吧
Yu,
小玉
if I stayed at home,
我总在家待着吧
Erbai and others would come to see me
二白他们就总要来看我
and buy things for me.
给咱买这买那的
It's not easy for them to make money.
他们赚钱也挺不容易的
So I want to earn more money
所以咱也得好好赚钱
and return
买点儿啥
their favor.
回馈回馈人家吧
What's more,
再说了
I can earn money this time
我这次去拉货
for delivering goods.
还能赚点儿钱回来
I heard them say
我听说那边的
the top-scholar cakes of Fengjing are delicious.
枫泾状元糕特别好吃
I'll bring some cakes back
我到时候给你
to you
和二白他们
and Erbai then.
一人带一份回来
Alright.
行
You're a good person.
就你心肠好
But I'm worrying about you.
可我就是担心你
Make sure you eat well.
你得好好吃饭啊
I got you.
知道了
Dongbao,
冬宝
think over the baby's name
那你空的时候
whenever you are free.
帮孩子想想名字呗
Once you name it,
早点定好了
I could talk to it
我也能早点
by its name.
隔着肚子叫他
OK.
行
I'll think hard.
那我路上一有空我就想
I will come up with 3 options for you
保证回来之前
before I come back.
想好三个名字给你选
OK.
好
Let me listen to
那我得好好听听
my son.
我儿子的声音
It maybe a baby girl.
万一是女儿呢
That's good, too.
也行
I like both.
我都喜欢
Don't worry about me.
别担心我
Wait for me.
等我回来
Minmin.
珉敏
Dad.
爸爸
it's the eight-treasure rice pudding in it.
这里面装的是八宝饭
Your friend is pregnant,
你朋友不是说怀孕了吗
so, I bring some more for her.
我也给她装了一些
Thank you, dad.
谢谢爸爸
Hurry back.
快去快回
Wait,
对
what would you like to eat as dinner?
晚上想吃什么呀
I want to have some soup.
想喝汤
I want warm soup made by yellow croaker.
热乎乎的黄鱼汤
I got it.
晓得了
I'll cook it for you.
我去给你熬
I'll go back home soon.
我很快就回来了 爸
OK.
晓得了
Did Dongbao tell you
冬宝说了吗
when he would go back home?
哪天回来啊
He said it just needs 2 or 3 days.
他说就去两三天
Maybe he will come back tomorrow.
明天应该就回来了吧
Dongbao said that
冬宝说从金山卫
he'd bring tasty food back from Jinshanwei.
给我们带好吃的回来
Minmin,
珉敏姐
the rice pudding is so delicious.
这个八宝饭真好吃
It's sweet.
好甜啊
It's my dad's cook.
这是我爸爸做的
You have a good appetite.
我看你胃口还挺好的
I don't know why.
我也不知道怎么回事儿
Others vomit a alot when they are pregnant.
人家怀孕都恶心
But I'm different.
我倒是不影响
I'm full of vigor.
干什么都有精神
That's very good sign.
那多好
You have a good appetite and the baby feels happy.
你胃口好 宝宝也开心
Have you given a name?
宝宝的名字想好了吗
Not yet.
还没有
Dongbao said that
冬宝说
he would think about it on his way.
他在路上有空就想
And he made sure that he could offer me 3 names.
保证回来给我三个选
You must be very happy.
瞧把你美的
Get out of the car.
下车
Go back home.
你就别送了
It's cold outside.
外头冷 别再冻着
It doesn't matter.
没事儿
I'll go with you till the end of the alley.
送你到弄堂口
I should have some exercise.
正好我多活动活动
OK, you should.
好 你也走两步
Brother Lu,
鲁大哥
you've come back from Jinshanwei.
你们从金山卫回来了
Where's Dongbao?
冬宝呢
We didn't go to Jinshanwei.
我们没去金山卫啊
Didn't Dongbao tell you?
冬宝回家没告诉你吗
He didn't go back home at all.
冬宝没回家呀
Really?
没回家
Then where did he go?
那他去哪儿了
Didn't he go with you
不是跟你们一块儿
to haul goods in Jinshanwei?
去金山卫拉货了吗
Don't mention it.
别提了
When we gathered that night,
那天晚上集合
the boss said the business was canceled.
老板说买卖取消了
So, we went back home
我们当时 那
after that.
那就各回各家了
Maybe
冬宝
Dongbao had another work
是不是又找着
to do.
别的活儿干了
No.
没有啊
Lu.
鲁大哥
Catch up
走了 来
I'm coming.
来了
I have something to do.
我还有事儿
Yu,
小玉
Keep asking the others.
你找其他人打听一下
I gotta go.
我先走了啊
No.
不是
He neither hauled goods nor went home.
他没去拉货 也没回家
Where could he be?
那他能去哪儿啊
Yu, don't worry.
小玉 你别着急
Will it possible for Dongbao
你想想冬宝有没有可能
to go to another team?
去别的车队
Minmin, his hand was injured
珉敏姐 他手又受伤了
and I'm pregnant now.
我又怀了孩子
He wouldn't go anywhere
他不可能不打声招呼
without telling me.
就乱跑
And he left
再说那天集合
in the middle of night.
都是深夜了
Where would he go?
他能去哪儿啊
Did he have some trouble
那他走之前
or met someone
有没有遇到什么事儿
before he left home?
或者碰到什么人
Let's talk in the room.
我们进屋说
Take care.
你慢点儿
Minmin,
珉敏姐
Dongbao had found some smuggling goods
冬宝那天晚上
in the warehouse that night.
在仓库发现了些走私品
He said it related to the military supplies.
他说是打仗用的东西
And he reported to the Shanghai Customs District immediately.
当时就去江海关举报了
Well,
你说
did it bring some trouble
会不会是那件事情
to him?
惹麻烦了
What's that?
是什么东西
It was a case,
是只箱子
in which Dongbao said there were bristles,
冬宝说里边是猪鬃
and some
还有一些
tungsten things.
乌黑乌黑的什么砂
tungsten ore.
钨砂
Yes, it is.
对 就是钨砂
Where did you find the case?
那具体在什么地方
The No.1 warehouse in Shiliupu Wharf.
十六铺码头一号仓库
It's near the warehouse
就是我平时
I'm working.
干活的仓库附近
OK.
好
Wait for me here.
你在屋里等着我
I'll go for the captain.
我去找队长
I'll go with you.
我跟你一块儿去
I can tell the captain
我能把那天晚上的事情
what happened that night.
都跟队长说
OK, let's go.
好 我们走
Take it easy.
你也别太着急
No matter what happened,
不管怎么样
if the captain is informed,
我们给队长说
he'll help us.
队长是会帮我们的
What's the matter?
怎么了
She is called Yu.
叫小玉
Yu?
小玉
Do you know her?
有没有印象
She is over there.
那不那儿呢吗 那个
The lady over there.
那个就是
Listen, go straight and don't look back.
听我的往前走 别回头
Qiang,
小强
Li,
阿力
she is there.
就是她
Run.
快跑
Get her.
追
Hurry.
快
Go.
走
Climb over..
上去
What about you?
你怎么办
Don't worry about me.
没事儿 你别管我了
Run away.
你上去
Stop.
站住
Run, Yu, don't worry.
小玉快跑 别管我
You two, go.
你俩 上
Go ahead.
往前呀
Chang, she ran away.
昌哥 人跑了
Catch her.
快追呀
Had Mr. Hua told you
华秘书跟你说过
how long we would stay here?
我们要待多久吗
It won't be so long.
待不了几天
He'll attend meetings
他下星期
next week in Nanjing.
在南京还有好几个会呢
Are you the head of the freight transport company?
你是货运公司的负责人
Yes.
是
I'm responsible to this freight.
这次送货我负责
My last name is Zhong.
我姓钟
How are the goods?
现在货装得怎么样了
It's almost ready.
都装得差不多了
It needs 10 more minutes.
还有十来分钟就装好了
[OK, hurry up.]
行 一定要抓紧时间
[Don't delay the schedule.]
不要耽误了进程
[OK.]
好嘞
[Don't worry.]
哥您放心啊
[I'll give it you in the car.]
上车我把东西给你
[This is the traffic permit that exempts you from inspection.]
这个是免检通行证
[Tell the driver it is tea on the car.]
告诉司机车上是茶叶
[Answer the same if the customs police ask.]
关卡问了都这么说
[Anti-smuggling Dpt. Of General Maritime Customs Service Administration]
江海关总税务司
[in Shanghai Customs District.]
缉私科
Public Security Bureau in Shanghai.
上海市公安局
With the 2 seals,
有这么两个章
no one would inspect us
过关卡的时候
when passing the customs?
就没有人查我们了
Yes.
对
They'll let you pass
他们看到上面盖的章
having seen the seals.
就会放行
Take this pass,
这个通行证你拿好了
and I'll keep
这份货单
this list of cargo.
我留下
OK.
好
Sir,
哥
where is the cargo going?
这批货送到什么地方
Japanese HBS.
日本人的弘济善堂
It must be delivered before 2:00 p.m.
下午两点之前必须送到
After arriving,
到了目的地之后
hand over your pass
你的通行证和我的货单
and my cargo list together to
都要一起交给
Mr. Feng of Criminal Investigation Dept.
十六铺分局
at Shiliupu Police Station.
刑警科的冯科长
Don't lose it.
千万别弄丢了
There is a layer of tea
货箱的上面
covering the real goods,
都盖有一层茶叶
and the real goods are beneath the tea.
下面才是这些东西
[I suppose they want to]
我估计他们是想
[sell these goods to Japan]
以茶叶的名目
[in the guise of tea.]
把这些货物卖去日本
Officer Luo,
骆警官
nice to meet you again.
又见面了
Let's be frank.
咱们打开天窗说亮话
You were the one who pretended to be Peng's wife
那天跟在华桢身边
bu the side of Hua Zhen that day,
假扮彭记者老婆的人
weren't you?
是你吧
Where's the journalist and his wife?
记者和他老婆人在哪儿
I don't know.
不知道
These two are murderers.
这两个人可是杀人犯
You've been with them
你从在造船所医院
since the dockyard hospital.
就跟他们混在一起
You don't know?
你不知道
I don't.
我不知道
You visited Tian Dongbao's wife.
你去见田冬宝老婆
What did she tell you?
她跟你说什么了
We talked about cooking.
我们聊了做饭的事
Does it interest you?
你也想听
[All checked,]
全部验过了
[no problem.]
没问题
[Then according to the old rules,]
那就按照老规矩
[settle all payments]
货物安全抵达之后
[after cargo's safe arrival.]
再结清货款
[We'll rely on the escort]
进城这一路上
[of Deputy Director Tan]
就靠谭副局长
[on the way to the down town.]
保驾护航了
[Don't worry.]
您放心
[My men]
我的人
[have told the van fleet.]
已经跟车队交代好了
[There was a little disturbance]
前两天
[in the warehouse]
仓库发生了
[two days ago.]
一点儿小风波
[Deputy Director Tan has solved it.]
谭副局长已经解决
[But I]
我呢
[am still a little worried.]
还是有些不太放心
This is the last batch of cargo today,
今天这是最后一批货
and when it arrives in the down town,
等这批货也运到城里
my vessel should be there, too.
我的船应该也到了
I hope we can leave
希望装船之后
as soon as possible after loading,
能够尽快出发
so as to avoid any more uncertainties,
免得再有变数
OK.
好的
Well,
这个
I'll coordinate with Shanghai Customs District,
我去跟江海关协调
Although there was
这次虽然
something unpleasant midway this time,
中途发生了一些不愉快
the cargo fortunately wasn't affected.
但好在货没有受影响
Mr. Hua,
华秘书
I hope our following business
希望我们之后的交易
won't be affected neither.
也不会受到影响
[The Ministry of the Army]
陆军省
[would also like to]
还希望跟贵公司
discuss a new order with you
商量一个新订单
for additional tungsten ore
增加钨砂的订货量
and tung oil.
再新增一批桐油
Do you have interest,
不知道华秘书
Mr. Hua?
有兴趣吗
As long as my company shows willing,
只要公司没问题
I'm OK.
我就没问题啊
[But all deals]
但是生意的事情
[should be presented]
要和公司的股东
[to the company's shareholders.]
一起商量才可以
[I believe that]
可是我相信
[as long as the price is profitable,]
只要价格合理
[we are willing to cooperate in good faith,]
大家都愿意精诚合作
[and collective prosperity.]
人人致富嘛
You are so frank,
真直接啊
Mr. Hua.
华秘书
Wish us a happy cooperation.
合作愉快
Thank you for your hard work.
拜托了
[Welcome back.]
到了
[Bro.]
哥
[Is everything OK?]
怎么样 路上顺利吗
[Why the posture?]
坐得这么规矩
[Are you a guest?]
你是客人啊
[You really have fun in Shanghai, don't you?]
这次来上海玩高兴了
[You played yourself into jail.]
把自己都玩到牢房里了
[Everything will be worked out.]
事情一定会解决
[I know.]
知道了
[You can choose to stay out of politics]
政治你可以不插手
[but you have to stay sensitive]
但是你不能不敏感
[and cautious.]
不谨慎
[You are the son of the Undersecretary of the Ministry of Military Affairs]
你是军政部次长的儿子
[So, don't say]
这些话
[these words again]
以后就算在家里
[even at home.]
也不要说了
[As long as the price is profitable,]
只要价格合理
[we are willing to cooperate in good faith,]
大家都愿意精诚合作
[and collective prosperity.]
人人致富嘛
Feng Sir,
冯哥
you should have known
你应该也猜出来了
the relationship between
这骆珉敏和华桢的关系
Luo Minmin and Hua Zhen.
可不一般呀
Do you think
那你看这事儿
we should report this
要不要跟谭副局长
to Deputy Director Tan?
汇报一声
He is working at Wusong Port,
他在吴淞口办事儿
and I will call him later.
我一会儿会给他打电话
Well,
不是
are we really going to do this?
咱真的要这么干吗
As Deputy Director Tan said before,
谭副局长说过了
I can follow my ideas.
事情就按照我的想法办
If you decide to tell me,
你想好什么时候开口
ring the bell.
什么时候就拉这个铃
Ring the Bell,
拉铃
and you can live,
你就能活命
or,
不然
you will freeze to death here
你冻死在这儿
and be a Jane Doe at best.
最多是一具无名女尸
This place is cold,
这地方挺冷的
just
正好
to help you
适合骆警官
cool down.
在这儿好好冷静冷静
Close the door.
关门
[Wake up.]
醒醒
[We've noticed you for a long time.]
我们早都注意到你了
[You don't work for]
你根本不是
[our freight company.]
我们货运公司的人
[Who are you?]
你到底什么人
[I saw you]
我刚才看见你
[rummaging in the van just now,]
偷偷在车厢里边翻东西
[and sneaking in it]
还鬼鬼祟祟
[for a long time.]
在上面待了好半天
[Are you trying to get in there]
你是不是想混进去
[and steal something?]
偷东西啊
[If you don't speak, I'll call the police.]
不说话找刑警去了
[You don't need to call the police.]
不用通知警察
[The youngest one]
你们三个老板中
[of your three bosses is my brother.]
最年轻的是我哥哥
[I'm here for him.]
我是来找他的
[Please ask him to come over,]
你们让他过来一趟
[and he'll thank you.]
他会感谢你们的
What's your brother's name?
你哥叫什么
Goodbye.
再见
That's all for now.
先这样
What's up?
有事儿吗
Is the gentleman in Chinese tunic suit
车上穿中山装这位先生
Mr. Hua?
是姓华吗
What's up?
你有什么事儿
Someone wants to meet him.
有人找他
Mr. Hua, someone wants to meet you.
华秘书 有人找
Boss, we just caught a man,
老板 我们刚抓了个人
and thought he was a thief,
以为是个小偷
but he said he is your brother,
但是 他说他是您弟弟
and asked us
还让我们
to take you to meet with him alone.
带您单独去见他
He said he is Hua Zhen.
对了 他说他叫华桢
Where is he?
人呢
We brought him to the office.
带到办公室了
Boss, is he your brother?
老板 他是你弟弟吗
I promised them
我答应了他们
you'd thank them as long as
只要不把我交给警察
they don't hand me over to the police.
你就会感谢他们的
Give them money.
给钱吧
My life is worth so little?
我的命就值这么点钱啊
Thank you, boss.
谢谢老板
Take them away.
带他们走
Wait,
等一下
this has nothing to do with them,
这件事跟他们俩没关系
so let them go.
放了他们
Just go.
走吧
Let's go.
走走走
You get out, too.
你们也出去
What are you doing here?
你来这儿干什么
And you?
你呢
How much money do you earn
今天这趟生意
from this business today?
你又挣了多少钱
What did Peng Ganwen's wife
彭记者的太太
say to you?
跟你说什么了
It's not Mrs. Peng.
不是彭太太
Then who is it?
那是谁
Didn't Tan Shiyuan tell you
谭施远没有告诉你吗
that Journalist Peng
彭记者已经
has been rescued by me?
被我救了出去
And now I know
你们为什么
why you kidnapped
要绑架彭记者
Journalist Peng.
我现在也知道了
I am a soldier
我是军人
and I will be the first to go to the frontline
一旦中日开战
if China and Japan go to War.
我会第一个上战场
I can't believe my brother
我不相信自己的哥哥
would smuggle military supplies to Japanese
会走私军需品给日本人
and allow them to
让他们有一天
turn the smuggled tungsten ore
把走私来的钨砂桐油
and tung oil into shells
变成炮弹
and drop them on my head.
炸回到我的头上来
So I have to see in person.
所以我要来看看
I'm convinced now.
现在我相信了
Hua Zhen,
华桢
maybe you think
也许你认为
all people and things
所有的人和事
are either good or bad,
只分好坏
right or wrong,
对错
black or white,
非黑即白
but I tell you,
但是我告诉你
most of the time,
绝大部分的时候
it's just the two good man of us
只是我们两个好人
working in
在为不同的立场
different positions.
做事而已
What's your
那你的不同立场
different position?
又是什么
My position is
我的立场
always the Hua family.
永远是华家
So all our families
所以家里人
know this?
知道这件事儿
Mom doesn't know.
妈妈不知道
Dad was also a soldier.
爸爸也是军人
He fought in the Northern Expedition with the former premier,
他随先总理参加过北伐
and he knew how difficult it was
他知道中国走到统一
for China to achieve unification.
是如何地艰辛
Did those hardships end up
难道那些艰辛到了最后
being for the sake of today's business?
就是为了今天这些生意
The great adventure
伟大的冒险事业
had been accomplished,
已经完成了
and everyone wants to
人人都想从里面
take some profits from it.
分出一点儿利益
What's wrong with that?
怎么了
Why can't we?
不行吗
You don't understand this,
你不理解这件事情
but it doesn't mean it's wrong.
不代表它就是错的
It's just
仅仅是因为
you can't understand.
你不理解而已
Don't think what you see
不要以为你看到的
and what you hear is the truth,
你听到的才是真理
and don't use it to judge me.
也不要用它来衡量我
What is the truth?
到底什么才是真理
Is there a second option
难道在民族存亡面前
when we face the possible fall of the nation?
还有第二个选择吗
And if we even need to
如果连这件事情
talk about positions on this matter,
还要谈立场
talk about right and wrong,
谈好坏 谈对错
we are fundamentally different.
那我们根本就是两路人
I'm your brother.
我是你哥哥
We just have different ideas.
我们只是观念不同
Don't regard me
不要轻易把我
as your enemy so easily.
当成你的敌人
This is not a concept, but a bottom line.
这不是观念 这是底线
"Internal disunity dissolves at the threat of external invasion."
兄弟阋墙 外御其侮
Communists have been pressed
共产党已经被你们
by you to the end,
逼到山穷水尽了
but still spare no efforts
还在尽最后一丝努力
to resist against Japanese.
团结抗日
While the pillars of our party and state
我们的党国栋梁
smuggle military supplies
却在偷偷走私军需品
to the Japanese.
给日本人
"Cooperate in good faith, and collective prosperity."
精诚合作 人人致富
How am I suppsed to understand you?
你让我怎么理解你
Do you want to be a traitor
难道你想做
and a flunky of the Japanese?
日本人的汉奸和走狗吗
What are you saying?
你说什么你
Don't think I won't beat you
别认为你在军校
as you learned something
学了点儿东西
in military school.
我就不敢动你
You go back to school by my car now.
你现在坐我的车回学校
Mom told me before my departure,
妈妈出门前特意交代我
that no matter what happens,
说无论出什么事情
I have to protect you.
都要我保护着你
You can go back to school
你现在能毫发无损地
unscathed now,
回到学校
because I still remember
就是因为我还记着
you are my brother.
你是我弟弟
Since I was little,
从小到大
I've always been knowing
我一直知道自己
what I was missing.
缺失的是什么
I don't have companionship from parents,
我没有父母的陪伴
and I don't have a family
没有一起吃饭
have dinner at table, and talk.
一起说话的家庭
But I have an elder brother.
但我有一个哥哥
When I got stuck in the car,
当我被困在车里的时候
he would pull the door down
他会亲手
to get me out.
把门拽下来救我出来
And when no one
在没人同意
would let me join the navy,
我去海军的时候
he would strive for my dream
他会为了我的梦想
against everyone.
跟所有人争取
When I reported to School of Mining Command,
电雷学校报到那天
he drove me to school
他开了两天两夜的车
for straight two days and nights,
送我去学校
and took photos with me at the school gate.
抱着我在学校门口照相
You are the only person
你是我在这个家里
I trust and depend on in this family.
唯一信任和依赖的人
Bro,
哥
why you?
为什么是你
I don't live
我不是活在
in a utopia,
乌托邦里的人
and I know someone
我知道也许有人
might have been doing this,
一直在做这样的事情
but why you?
但为什么是你
You and me
你和我
are totally different.
是完全不同的两种人
I know we are different,
我知道我们不同
and I never think of
我也没想成为
being a person like you.
你这样子的人
But this never affects
但这从来没有影响过
your image in my heart.
你在我心里的样子
I can take a bullet for you,
我可以为你挡子弹
but what you saw today
但是你今天看到的一切
won't change.
不会改变
It won't change today,
今天不会变
and neither in the future.
明天也不会变
Hua Zhen,
华桢
you are in danger now.
你现在的处境很危险
Go back to school.
回学校吧
Just go.
走吧
Go.
走啊
I didn't want to tell you
本来我不打算告诉你的
that Luo Minmin was arrested.
骆珉敏被抓起来了
What?
你说什么
If you go back to school now,
如果你现在回学校
I will call them
我可以替你打电话
and ask them
给他们求情
to keep her alive.
留她一条命
If you continue to waste time here,
如果你继续在这里耽搁
she probably won't survive tonight.
她大概活不过今晚
What's wrong with Luo Minmin?
骆珉敏怎么了
You take my car back to school now.
你现在坐我的车回学校
I have something to do here.
我在这里还有事情
As long as my men tell me
直到他们打电话给我
that they see you entering the school,
说亲眼看到你进学校了
I'll immediately call them
我马上给他们打电话
to let her go.
让他们放人
What happened to Luo Minmin?
骆珉敏怎么了
Where is she?
她在哪儿
Answer me!
说话
You stay a minute longer,
你多逗留一分钟
and she'll die a minute sooner.
她就早死一分钟
Is it Tan Shiyuan or Nakamura Naoki?
是谭施远还是里见直树
Or you?
还是你
What happened to Luo Minmin?
骆珉敏到底怎么了
You're wasting her time.
你在耽误她的时间
Made up your mind?
想好了
Is she alive?
她还活着
Alive for now.
现在还活着
You promise me.
你保证
I promise,
我保证
as long as you go back to school,
只要你现在回学校
I'll ask them to let her go.
我马上让他们放人
Send him back to school
送他回学校
and tell Master Hu
跟胡教官说
not to allow him to step out of the school
没有我的命令
without my order.
不准踏出学校半步
Yes,sir.
是 是
And,
还有
never repeat
刚才你说过的那些话
what you said.
绝不要再提